# Julia (Jules) Fowler

### SOFTWARE ENGINEER |

they · them · theirs

□ (+1) 512 963-9951 | ☑ jfowler@stsci.edu | 备 http://www.stsci.edu/~jfowler/ | ᡚ julesfowler | orcid: 0000-0002-0726-9323

### Summary

**Astronomer**: space-based instrumentation and exoplanet astronomy focused.

Software Engineer: Python and Git expert, Linux enthusiast.

**Instructor**: Software Carpentry Instructor and Python training developer.

Activist: member of the AAS committee for Sexual and Gender Minorities in Astronomy.

### **Certifications & Skills**

Certified SCRUM Master SCRUM Alliance

**Certified Software Carpentry Instructor** Software Carpentry

**Laser Safety Certification** Laser Institute of America

Python expert

Git expert

conda expert

bash expert

Linux expert

Mac OS expert

Windows expert

LaTeX expert

Mathematica advanced

Markdown advanced

HTML advanced

**Julia** beginner

IDL beginner

IRAF/PyRAF beginner

JavaScript beginner

CSS beginner

### Research Experience \_\_\_\_

#### **Russel B. Makidon Optics Lab**

Baltimore, MD

October 2018 - PRESENT

SPACE TELESCOPE SCIENCE INSTITUTE (STSCI)

• Principal Investigator of the Generalized Lab Architecture for Restructured Optical Experiment (G.L.A.R.E.) – an STSCI Director's Discretionary Research project to build autonomous experiment software for LUVIOR-like coronagraphy experiments.

- Wrote pure Python controller software for nPoint tip/tilt controller as part of a optics testbed.
- Provided deomnstartions of small scale coronagraphic test bench (babyCAT) at AAS and Astronomy on Tap.
- Advisors : Rémi Soummer & Marshall Perrin

### **Exoplanet Characterization Toolkit**

Baltimore, MD

STScI

May 2017 - PRESENT

- Developed first on-the-fly observation planning tool for exoplanet observations with James Webb Space Telescope (JWST).
- · Built an HDF5 database and web interface for the Goyal et.al.grid of forward model transmission spectra.
- Managed ExoCTK web application from server-side to front end development, and converted existing codebase to best Python practices.
- Advisors: Kevin Stevenson & Nikole Lewis

### **Space Telescope Advanced Research Group for the Atmospheres of Transiting Exoplanets**

Baltimore, MD

SISCI

Oct. 2017 - Oct. 2018

- Wrote open source pipeline to reduce WFC3/IR spatial scan data, fit transit parameters with a Markov-Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) simulation, calculate Bayesian statistics, and produce transmission spectra.
- Introduced the group to and implemented best Python and open source software practices.
- Advisors: Hannah Wakeford & Jeff Valenti

#### Wide Field Camera Three Instrument Team

Baltimore, MD

STScI Aug. 2016 - PRESENT

- Lead of the WFC3 Quicklook project, developing automated monitors and calibration software on a large-scale web and database application.
- Principal Investigator of eleven HST calibration proposals.
- Re-factored and automated outdated software, including various Python, IDL, and IRAF/Pyraf monitors.
- Created user guides and tools for WFC3/IR slitless spectroscopy data reduction and anomaly tracking.
- Advisors: Elena Sabbi & Sylvia Baggett

Tufts University Somerville, MA

SUMMER SCHOLAR & SENIOR THESIS

May 2015 - July 2016

- Compared energy contribution of low energy radio jets to gas outflows in AGN.
- Used slurm parallel cluster computing and CASA to reduce a terrabtye of multi-band Very Large Array (VLA) data.
- Detailed reduction and small numbers statics in a senior honors thesis.
- Advisor: Anna Sajina

**University of Texas, Austin** 

Austin, TX

May 2012 - August 2013

RESEARCH INTERN

- Performed stellar evolution and structure research on Betelgeuese and Wolf-Rayet stars.
- Created computational models using MESA star.
- Advisor: Craig Wheeler

### Work Experience \_

### **Space Telescope Science Institute**

Baltimore, MD

SOFTWARE ENGINEER II Aug. 2016 - PRESENT

- Member of the Wide Field Camera Three Instrument Team and involved with multiple science projects across the institute.
- Started SpaceGAYs, the first LGBT+ affinity group at STScI, and member of the Invision Diversity Working Group.
- Designed Advanced Python training with outside vendor, and gave SWC inspired introductory Python and Git training.

### **Tufts University, Department of Physics and Astronomy**

Somerville, MA

**TEACHING ASSISTANT & HOMEWORK GRADER** 

Sept. 2014- July 2016

- Lab TA for introductory mechanics and class TA for general audience astronomy seminar.
- Graded homework for introductory mechanics and electricity and magnetism.

#### **Tufts University, Academic Resource Center**

Somerville, MA

TUTOR & EXAM ASSISTANT

Sept. 2014- July 2016

- Tutored individual students and led study groups for introductory physics, calculus, and linear algebra.
- Assisted students with accessible exam accommodations.

### **Education**

Tufts University Somerville, MD

B.S. ASTROPHYSICS & PHILOSOPHY Sept. 2012 - May 2016

- · Graduated with High Thesis Honors.
- Dean's List 2013, 2015

### **University of Maryland, College Park**

College Park, MD

• High Energy Astronomy.

SUMMER TRANSIENT STUDENT

**University of Texas, Austin** 

Austin. TX

Spring 2017

Summer 2013, 2014

· Calculus II & III, Linear Algebra, Differential Equations, Logic

### Awards & Grants\_

### **GRANTS**

| 2019 | 515ct Data Science innovation initiative Grant, Director's Discretionary Research Fund Call for projects | Baltimore, MD  |
|------|--|----------------|
|      | with a focus on data science and interesting computational problems                                      |                |
| 2015 | Tufts Summer Scholar Grant, call for summer long indepedent research projects                            | Somerville, MA |
| 2015 | Tufts Center for Stem Diversity Grant, grant to create the first collegiate queer science speaker series | Somerville, MA |

### **AWARDS**

| 2016 | Tufts University Pride on the Hill, for contributions to LGBT+ climate    | Somerville, MA |
|------|---|----------------|
| 2015 | Tufts Multicultural Service Award, for contributions to diversity efforts | Somerville, MA |

### **Committees**

| 2019 | Inclusive Astronomy II, member of the Science Organizing Committee         | Baltimore, MD  |
|------|--|----------------|
| 2019 | STScI/AURA Exoplanet Astronomer hiring committee, member                   | Baltimore, MD  |
| 2019 | STScI Information Technology Head hiring committee, member                 | Baltimore, MD  |
| 2018 | AAS Committee for Sexual and Gender Minorities in Astronomy (SGMA), member |                |
| 2016 | out in STEM (oSTEM) @ Tufts, president and founder                         | Somerville, MA |
| 2015 | Tufts Society of Physics Students , president                              | Somerville, MA |
| 2014 | Tufts Queer Students Association, treasurer                                | Somerville, MA |

### **Teaching**

### Software Carpentry at the AAS

INSTRUCTOR

Taught astronomy focused Python and bash at the 233RD AAS meeting.

#### **Software Carpentry at the New York Academy of Sciences**

INSTRUCTOR

• Taught general science focused Python and Git at NYAS.

### **Tufts University Concepts of the Cosmos**

CLASS TA

• Class TA for the introductory/general education astronomy seminar.

### **Tufts University Physics 1 & Physics 11**

Lab TA

- Lab TA for the introductory mechanics courses with and without calculus.

Seattle, WA

Jan. 2019

New York, NY

Jan. 2019

Somerville, MA

Spring 2016

Somerville, MA

Fall 2015

### **Publications and Presentations** —

### **PUBLICATIONS**

## Disentangling the Planet from the Star in Late-Type M Dwarfs: A Case Study of TRAPPIST-1g

Wakeford, H. R.; Lewis, N. K.; **Fowler, J.**; Bruno, G.; Wilson, T. J.; Moran, S. E.; Valenti, J.; Batalha, N. E.; Filippazzo, J.; Bourrier, V.; Hörst, S. M.; Lederer, S. M.; de Wit, J.

The Astronomical Journal, Volume 157, Issue 1, article id. 11, 14 pp. (2019)

### WFC3/UVIS Gain Stability Results for Cycles 24 and 25

FOWLER, J.

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2018-17, 24 pages

### The Cosmic Ray That Wouldn't Quit: Correcting Cosmic Rays in Overscan Pixels

FOWLER, JULIA

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2017-12, 7 pages

### Monitoring the WFC3/UVIS Relative Gain with Internal Flatfields

FOWLER, J.; BAGGETT, S.

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2017-08, 17 pages

### The Betelgeuse Project: constraints from rotation

WHEELER, J. CRAIG; NANCE, S.; DIAZ, M.; SMITH, S. G.; HICKEY, J.; ZHOU, L.; KOUTOULAKI, M.; SULLIVAN, J. M.; FOWLER, J. M. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 465, Issue 3, p.2654-2661, (2017)

### Analysis of Dragon's Breath and Scattered Light Detector Anomalies on WFC3/UVIS

FOWLER, JULIA; MARKWARDT, LARISSA; BOURQUE, MATTHEW; ANDERSON, JAY

Instrument Science Report WFC3 2017-02 (v.1), 14 pages

### **PRESENTATIONS**

#### Standardizing Exoplanet Analysis with the Exoplanet Characterization Tool Kit (ExoCTK) talk FOWLER, J.; STEVENSON, KEVIN B.; LEWIS, NIKOLE K.; FRAINE, JONATHAN D.; PUEYO, LAURENT; BRUNO, GIOVANNI; summer, 2018 Filippazzo, Joe; Hill, Matthew; Batalha, Natasha; Wakeford, Hannah; Bushra, Rafia American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #232 Advances on Hubble Wide Field Camera 3 Grism Calibration and Slitless Spectroscopy poster **Analysis** FOWLER, JULIA; BRAMMER, GABRIEL; RYAN, RUSSELL; DEUSTUA, SUSANA; PIRZKAL, NOR winter, 2018 American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #231, id. 355.19 The Exoplanet Characterization ToolKit (ExoCTK) poster STEVENSON, KEVIN; FOWLER, JULIA; LEWIS, NIKOLE K.; FRAINE, JONATHAN; PUEYO, LAURENT; VALENTI, JEFF; BRUNO, winter, 2018 Giovanni; Filippazzo, Joseph; Hill, Matthew; Batalha, Natasha E.; Bushra, Rafia American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #231, id. 148.14

## Do Radio Jets Contribute to Driving Ionized Gas Outflows in Moderate Luminosity Type 2 AGN?

winter, 2016

poster

American Astronomical Society, AAS Meeting #227, id.243.08

FOWLER, JULIA; SAJINA, ANNA; LACY, MARK